Finding Aid for William Lucas Papers 1965-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Lucas Papers 1965-1986, 1975-1986
Lucas, William, 1928-
1 oversize folders
34 linear feet
Wayne County sheriff, 1969-1982, Wayne County Executive, 1983-1986, and Republican candidate for governor of Michigan, 1986. Correspondence, subject files, clippings, videotapes, and photographs primarily concerning his work as sheriff and county executive, and his gubernatorial campaign.
87482 Aa 2 UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mr. Lucas (donor no. 7455 ) in June 1987.
The collection is open for research.
William Lucas, whose career in public service has spanned 35 years, was born in Harlem, in 1928. When he was orphaned in his early teens (his West Indian immigrant parents died within a year of each other), he went to live with and was raised by an aunt. He attended Morris High School in the Bronx, and starred on the school track team. Because of his track skill he was offered a number of collegiate athletic scholarships, and accepted one from Manhattan College. He was the first in his family to go to college, and graduated with honors, in 1952, with a Bachelor of Science degree.
After graduation, Lucas spent several years as a teacher and welfare case worker in New York City. In 1953 he joined the New York Police Department, where he remained for nine years, often working undercover in Harlem. From his experiences with the city legal system he decided to become a lawyer, and attended Fordham University at night. He received his law degree in 1962, and at the graduation ceremony he met Robert Kennedy, who offered him a job in the Justice Department. Lucas accepted and spent two years as an investigator in the civil rights division. He then joined the Federal Bureau of Investigation as a special agent, stationed first in Cincinnati, and later in Detroit. He left the Bureau in 1967 to become Wayne County undersheriff, and two years later was appointed Wayne County sheriff when Roman Gribbs vacated the position after winning election as mayor of Detroit. Lucas was elected Wayne County sheriff in his own right in 1970 and reelected twice thereafter, serving in that capacity for thirteen years. In 1982, he ran successfully for the newly-created office of Wayne County Executive. He served for four years as the chief officer of the third largest county in the United States.
Explaining that he was dismayed by the influence of special interests in the Democratic party, Lucas switched political affiliation to the Republican party in May 1985. He won the Republican gubernatorial primary in 1986, only the second Black in the history of the country to win a major party nomination for governor. He ran on a platform that stressed the historic nature of his candidacy, fiscal responsibility, and law and order, but lost the general election to the incumbent, Governor James Blanchard.
Lucas married his wife Evelyn while he was in high school. They have five children, three of whom are physicians. William Lucas currently (1987) works for a law firm in Detroit.
The William Lucas Papers consist of manuscript and audiovisual materials which primarily document economic and social affairs in Wayne County, when Lucas served as county executive, and Lucas's campaign for governor in 1986. There are few materials on Lucas's career prior to his service as Wayne County executive. His gubernatorial campaign is documented in a somewhat piecemeal fashion, and study of it would be enhanced by the use of oral interviews. Media coverage of the campaign, however, has been preserved quite thoroughly. The Lucas Papers (34 linear feet) are comprised of six series: Personal, Wayne County Offices, Political, Clippings, Videotapes, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1986.; Law enforcement--Michigan--Wayne County.; Lucas, William, 1928-; Sheriffs--Michigan--Wayne County.; Republican Party (Mich.); Wayne County (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Wayne County (Mich.). Sheriff Dept.; Wayne County (Mich.). Executive.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-Americans--Political life.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Engler, Coleen.; Law enforcement--Michigan--Wayne County.; Lucas, William, 1928-; Police--Michigan--Wayne County.; Political elections--1986.; Politics and government--1981-1990.; Reagan, Ronald.; Republican Party (Mich.); Wayne County (Mich.). Executive.; Wayne County (Mich.). Sheriff Dept.
Genre/Form:
Cartoons.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Personal
  The Personal series (2 folders) is the one to which the researcher should turn to learn about the many phases of Lucas's career. It contains biographical materials in the form of articles, resumes, membership certificates, and promotional materials on several of his children. One of the more interesting documents is a 1970 questionnaire filled out by Lucas for the Manhattan College Magazine. In it he discusses his collegiate experiences and how they shaped the principles and philosophies which guided him later in life. The series also contains materials related to Lucson Petroleum Corporation, of which Lucas was an original incorporator. The corporation was in the oil refining and distributing industry.
  - Biographical (includes memorabilia) (Box 1)
  - Lucson Petroleum Corporation (Box 1)
    includes correspondence and legal documents
- Wayne County Offices
  The Wayne County Offices series (1 linear foot) is divided into two subseries, one for each of the major county offices Lucas held, sheriff and county executive. They are arranged alphabetically by topic. The sheriff subseries contains materials which mostly pertain to major incidents which occurred while Lucas was in office. They include the battle between Lucas and Wayne County Commissioners over elimination of the Patrol and Investigation Division, and the "Rochester Incident" which involved a shootout between Wayne County sheriffs and Detroit policemen. There is also a very interesting transcript of the "Pingree Street Conspiracy Trial" of 1975, in which Detroit policemen and private citizens were tried for the sale of narcotics and conspiracy to obstruct justice.
  In the county executive subseries, five folders of manuscript materials contain scattered documents on Lucas's tenure. The correspondence file includes Lucas's responses to a variety of constituent concerns, and the interoffice memos provide a cursory look at media strategy, and budget and union contract issues during Lucas's first months in office. The researcher will note newsclippings and videotapes relating Lucas' work as Wayne County executive are filed in the Clippings and Tapes series. They are extremely important to any study of Lucas as county executive.
  - Sheriff
    - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - FBI Directorship Nomination 1977 (Box 1)
      (mostly clippings and letters of recommendation)
    - Patrol and Investigation (Box 1)
      (mostly legal materials re: 1981 controversy over elimination of the division; includes one audio tape)
    - Pingree Street Conspiracy Trial (narcotics conspiracy) (Box 1)
    - Rochester Incident (Box 1)
      (reports, correspondence, and clippings)
  - County Executive
    - General (Box 1)
    - Appointment Calendars 1984-1985 (Box 1)
      includes political engagements
    - Campaign for office (Box 1)
    - Correspondence undated, December 1982-February 1983, May 1983 (Box 1)
    - Interoffice Memos November 1982-November 1983 (Box 2)
    - White House, The (Box 2)
      (mostly routine correspondence)
- Political
  The Political series (1/2 linear foot) consists of materials related to Lucas's campaign for governor. It is also arranged alphabetically by topic, and while the manuscript materials do not provide in-depth coverage of the campaign, the researcher will benefit from use of the folders on finances, which in report form document early efforts to raise campaign funds; issues; speeches; and surveys of issues and voter preferences. There are again cross references to the important Clippings and Videotapes series.
  - Clippings (Box 2)
    see Clippings Series, boxes 3-12
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) undated, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Finances 1985, 5 volumes; 1 folders (Box 2)
    includes correspondence and reports
  - Issues (Box 2)
    includes position papers, completed questionnaire, and background materials
  - Speeches (Box 2)
    includes handwritten notes for two speeches, and typed text of speeches given upon joining Republican Party, and announcing for Governor
  - Surveys of issues and voter preferences 1985, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Tapes (Box 2)
    video, see Tapes Series, boxes 28-33
  - Travel Schedules October 1985, December 1986 trip to Washington to meet with Republican administration officials (Box 2)
  - Unity Agreement (copy of) (Box 2)
  - Volunteers (statewide listing) (Box 2)
- Clippings
  The Clippings series (10 linear feet) is a very comprehensive run of' newspaper coverage of Lucas's tenure as county executive and his political activities, including the gubernatorial campaign. The bulk of the series is comprised of clippings from the Detroit Free Press and Detroit News, but there is often coverage from other major papers around the state as well. The series is arranged chronologically, beginning in January 1983, and ending in November 1986. It is complete, with the exception of May and June 1986, for which clippings were not received. It is a valuable series on which to rely for developing a chronology of important events for those years, following the reaction around the state to his entrance into the Republican Party, and charting public opinion on his campaign for governor.
  - 1983
    - January (Box 3)
    - February (Box 3)
    - March (Box 3)
    - April (Box 3)
    - May (Box 3)
    - June (Box 3)
    - July (Box 4)
    - August (Box 4)
    - September (Box 4)
    - October (Box 4)
    - November (Box 4)
    - December (Box 4)
  - 1984
    - January (Box 4)
    - February (Box 5)
    - March (Box 5)
    - April (Box 5)
    - May, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - June, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - July (Box 5)
    - August, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - September (Box 6)
    - October, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - November (Box 6)
    - December (Box 6)
  - 1985
    - January (Box 7)
    - February (Box 7)
    - March (Box 7)
    - April (Box 7)
    - May, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - June, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - July (Box 8)
    - August (Box 9)
    - September (Box 9)
    - October (Box 9)
    - November (Box 9)
    - December (Box 9)
  - 1986
    - January, 2 folders (Box 10)
      includes late December clippings
    - February, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - March, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - April (Box 10)
      folder 1 of 3
    - April (Box 11)
      folders 2 and 3 of 3
    - July (Box 11)
    - August, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - September, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - October, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - November (Box 12)
- Videotapes
  The Videotapes series (21 linear feet) is the largest in the collection and is divided into three subseries. The Wayne County Executive subseries contains a run of public affairs programs entitled, "Wayne County: A New Perspective," which were produced while Lucas was county executive. They are videotapes and are arranged alphabetically by title. They cover an enormous range of topics and provide insight into economic and social concerns of the 1980s in one of the largest counties in the country. The form is generally that of a panel discussion on the topic by several area specialists, and often includes information on county programs overseen and/or initiated by Lucas. The researcher should consult the contents list to determine programs of interest. This subseries also contains a miscellaneous set of both audio and video tapes of activities of Executive Lucas, including various press conferences, speeches, and talk show appearances.
  The political subseries of the Videotapes series is arranged alphabetically by topic and consists of video tapes of phases of his gubernatorial campaign. Among the more interesting are his announcements of joining the Republican party and entering the governor's race, the Detroit Economic Club debate with James Blanchard, promotional spots used to develop voter loyalty and explain his stances on issues, and talk show appearances.
  The third subseries, labeled "Masters," are videotapes comprised of evening news segments from the ABC, CBS, and NBC affiliates in Detroit which focus on Lucas from the early months of 1984 to November 1986. While the emphasis is on his political activities, there is also very good coverage of his tenure as Wayne County executive. When used with the Political series and the Clippings series, the researcher is provided almost complete media coverage of Lucas's activities from 1983 through 1986.
  - Wayne County Executive
    - Wayne County: A New Perspective
      - Afro-American Museum (Box 13)
      - Afro-American Tour (Box 13)
      - Agriculture in Wayne County (also includes Detroit-Metro. Ceramic Tile) (Box 13)
      - Aids Scare (Box 13)
      - American Lung Association and Jim Mouth (Box 13)
      - Ask The Executive (Box 13)
      - Auto News World Expo (Box 13)
      - Auto Theft: The Chop Shop Break-Up (Box 13)
      - Belleville Lake: The Untold Story (Box 13)
      - Best of Wayne County: A New Perspective (Box 14)
      - Best of Wayne County: A New Perspective Part II (Box 14)
      - Bite Out of Rabies (Box 14)
      - Birthday Party (Box 14)
      - Blue Cross: Mutual or No Mutual (Box 14)
      - Breaking Down The Budget Battle (Box 14)
      - CEO State of the County Address (Box 14)
      - Capital Punishment (Box 14)
      - Chamber of Commerce: Foreign Trade Mission (Box 14)
      - Changing Voter Patterns (Box 15)
      - Charter Battle Brews (Box 15)
      - Chicago Tonight (Box 15)
      - Child I.D.: No Kidding Tonight (Box 15)
      - Close-Up: John D. O'Hair (Box 15)
      - Community Mental Health Programs (Box 15)
      - Concerns and Crime in Wayne County (Box 15)
      - County Care Provides Prevention (master, and re-edited Master) (Box 15)
      - County Parks Revive (Box 16)
      - County Parks Revive I (Box 16)
      - Crime Tax (Box 16)
      - Detroit Chamber of Commerce Debate (Blanchard vs. Lucas) (Box 16)
      - Discussion With the Women's Economic Club (Box 16)
      - Do You Know Your Commissioner? (Box 16)
      - Drain Commissioner: Elected or Appointed (Box 16)
      - Economic Future of Michigan (Box 16)
      - Economic Development Corporation (Box 16)
      - Educational Plans For Wayne County (Box 16)
      - Educational Visions For Wayne County (Box 17)
      - Emergency Preparedness (Box 17)
      - Exploring the Future of State and County Government through Debate (Box 17)
      - Fall Tour of Greenfield Village (Box 17)
      - Family in Today's Society, The (Box 17)
      - February 12th: A Historic Announcement (Lucas announcement for Governor) (Box 17)
      - First Two Years (Box 17)
      - First Two Years, Part II (Box 17)
      - Flight To The Future (Box 17)
      - Flooding Preparedness: Are You Ready (Box 17)
      - 4-H Program in Detroit: Growing Roots, The (Box 18)
      - Forgotten Victim of Crime, The (Box 18)
      - Future of Wayne County, The (Box 18)
      - Graying of Wayne County, The (Box 18)
      - Handgun Control (Box 18)
      - Healthy Outlook (Box 18)
      - History of Eloise (Box 18)
      - History of the Eloise Complex (Box 18)
      - How Landfills Work In Wayne County (Box 18)
      - How Will People Vote (Box 18)
      - Hunger (Box 18)
      - Hunger and Emergency Feeding In Wayne County (Box 19)
      - Infant Health and Infant Mortality (Box 19)
      - Juvenile Crime (Box 19)
      - Kids, Courts, and Crime (Box 19)
      - Kopy, Ed: Executive Corner (Box 19)
      - Legionnaires Disease Outbreak in Wayne County (Box 19)
      - Let's Talk About Sex (Box 19)
      - Lock Up (Box 19)
      - Look At The Wayne County Office on Aging, A (Box 19)
      - Lucas At Oakland Community College, Mr. Lucas Upfront (Box 20)
      - Metro Airport Celebrates (Box 20)
        master, and re-edited master
      - Metro Expansion (Box 20)
      - Minority Businesses Share Strategy For Success (Box 20)
      - Mother Waddles Christmas, A (Box 20)
      - Neo-Natal Care Unit At Wayne County General Hospital (Box 20)
      - New Avenues To Employment (Box 20)
      - New Avenues To Employment II (Box 21)
      - Old County Courthouse, The (Box 21)
      - Patient Care Management of Wayne County, The (Box 21)
      - Plymouth Orchard and Cider Mill, The (Box 21)
      - Prison Overflow Prompts Study (Box 21)
      - Prison Overflow Prompts Study-Part Two (Box 21)
      - Private Industry Corporation/Wayne County: Partnership For Progress (Box 21)
      - Prosecutor's Office (Box 21)
      - Renovation of the Old County Building, The (Box 21)
      - Riverview Highlands: A Landfill At Work, The (Box 22)
      - Road Commission (Box 22)
      - Roperti's Turkey Farm (Box 22)
      - Salt Mines of Wayne County, The (Box 22)
      - Say Yes on August 7th (Box 22)
      - Second Year Reflections (Box 22)
      - Skiing In Wayne County (Box 22)
      - Solid Waste: Landfills vs. Incineration (Box 22)
      - Southeast Michigan Visits Japan (Box 22)
      - State Issues In Wayne County (Box 23)
      - State Of The County Address (Box 23)
      - State Of The State Discussion (Box 23)
      - Summertime In Wayne County Parks (Box 23)
      - Surplus Commodity Distribution Program (Box 23)
      - Synthetic Drugs: The New Walking Death (Box 23)
      - Teen Suicide: Too Young To Die (Box 23)
      - Teenage Pregnancies: Problems and Solutions (Box 23)
      - This Is A Drill (Box 23)
      - This Is Only A Test (Box 24)
      - Transit In Motion (Box 24)
      - Transracial Adoption (Box 24)
      - WC3 (Box 24)
      - Wayne County Air Pollution Control Division (Box 24)
      - Wayne County Alcohol Task Force/Neo-Natal Care Unit (Box 24)
      - Wayne County General Hospital Lease Option Analyzed (Box 24)
      - Wayne County Morgue (Box 24)
      - Wayne County Morgue/Draper Hill/Detroit Tigers (Box 24)
      - Wayne County Roads Department (Box 25)
      - Wayne County Sheriff's Marine Patrol (Box 25)
      - Welcomes President Ronald Reagan (Box 25)
      - Welcomes State G.O.P. Convention (Box 25)
      - Wayne County Youth Development (Box 25)
      - Wayne County Youth Home (Box 25)
      - Wayne County Youth Home Overcrowding (Box 25)
      - Wayne County's German Heritage: The Dearborn Oktoberfest (Box 25)
      - Wayne State University (Box 25)
      - Whooping Cough (Box 25)
      - WIC (Women, Infants, Children) Program of the Wayne County Health Department (Box 26)
      - William Cahalan: 16 Years of Service (Box 26)
      - Winter Sports In Wayne County Parks (Box 26)
      - Woodcarver (Box 26)
      - Work of the Michigan Youth Corps Program, The (Box 26)
      - Year In Review: Lucas' First Year, The (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Recordings of inauguration, press conferences, speeches, talk shows, and visit by Margaret Heckler (Box 27)
      (not inventoried; includes 13 U-matic, 2 VHS, and 9 audio cassettes)
  - Political (Gubernatorial Race)
    - Announcements
      - Switch to Republican Party (Box 28)
      - Candidacy For Governor (Box 28)
    - Debate with James Blanchard (Box 28)
    - Press Conferences (Box 29)
    - Primary Victory Celebration (Box 29)
    - Promotional/Issue Spots (Box 29)
    - Ronald Reagan Visit (Box 30)
    - Republican Party State Convention (Box 30)
    - Talk Shows (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
      (unprocessed)
  - Masters
    - Channel 2, 12 tapes (Box 32)
    - Channel 4, 10 tapes
      - Tapes 1-6 (Box 32)
      - Tapes 7-10 (Box 33)
    - Channel 7, 12 tapes (Box 33)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (1 linear foot) includes images of Lucas and his family in the 1970s and 1980s, one snapshot taken while he was a special agent for the FBI, and a series of images from his tenure as Wayne County sheriff. The majority of the series, however, consists of photographs taken during his campaign for governor. They are arranged alphabetically by topic, and the researcher is advised to consult the contents list for specific images of interest.
  - Personal and Family (includes some negatives) (Box 34)
    (see also outsize UAm)
  - FBI (one snapshot of Lucas with an unidentified man) (Box 34)
  - Wayne County Sheriff (Box 34)
  - Political
    - Abraham, Spencer (Box 34)
    - Agriculture (Box 34)
    - Autoworkers (Lucas plant appearances) (Box 34)
    - Blanchard, Governor James (debate with Lucas) (Box 34)
    - Bush, Vice-President George (Box 34)
      includes slides
    - Engler, Colleen (Box 34)
    - Gaylord, Michigan (supporters) (Box 34)
    - Grand Rapids, Michigan (supporters) (Box 34)
    - Hawthorne Plant Press Conference September 9, 1986 (Box 34)
    - Indian Village Citizens For Better Government (Box 34)
    - Inkster, Michigan
      - Citizens For Better Government (Box 34)
      - Renaming Blanchette Middle School (Box 34)
    - Jackson, Michigan, Campaign Stops (Box 34)
    - Kalamazoo, Michigan, Campaign Stops (Box 34)
    - Legislators, State (Box 34)
    - Little Rock Baptist Church Rally (includes the Reverend Jim Holley) (Box 34)
    - Long's Convention, Lansing (Box 34)
    - Lucas, Father Larry, Sr. (brother of William Lucas) (Box 34)
    - Macomb County Press Conference (Box 34)
    - Madison Minority Alliance, MSU (Box 34)
    - Mayors, Michigan Cities (with Lucas, includes mayors of Benton Harbor, Grand Haven, and Port Huron) (Box 34)
    - Memorial Day Parade 1986 (Box 34)
    - Oakland County, Michigan, Campaign Stops (Box 34)
    - Patterson, Mari (Box 34)
    - Personalities (includes Deane Baker, Dick Chrysler, Dean O. Day, Robert Dole, Margaret Heckler, Thomas Hearns, Governor Kean, Jack Kemp, Coretta King, Jeane Kirkpatrick, Carl Levin, Ed Meese, Brooks Patterson, Lana Pollack, Pat Robertson, George Romney, Ronna Romney, Al Schmid, Peter Secchia, Guy Vander Jagt) (Box 34)
    - Primary Victory Celebration (Box 34)
    - Reagan, President Ronald (Box 34)
    - Redford, Michigan, Fair (Box 34)
    - Reporters (Box 34)
    - Republican Party
      - Candidates (Box 34)
      - Dinner (Box 34)
      - State Convention (Box 34)
    - Romulus, Michigan, Junior High School (Box 34)
    - Supersonic Transport Visit (Box 34)
    - Thirty-First District Republican Club (Box 34)
    - Miscellaneous (includes negatives) (Box 34)